<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To all the inhabitiants of the town of Youghal who are under the teaching of James Wood ...</title>
            <author>Sicklemore, James.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1657</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 38 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A60206</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3750</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R24541</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08244781</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08244781</idno>
            <idno type="VID">41149</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A60206)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 41149)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1240:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>To all the inhabitiants of the town of Youghal who are under the teaching of James Wood ...</title>
                  <author>Sicklemore, James.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>8 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1657?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Signed: James Sicklemore.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Youghal (Cork) --  Church history.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Greg Schutz</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:41149:1"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:41149:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <div type="author_to_inhabitants_of_Youghal">
               <p>To all the Inhabitants of the Town of <hi>Youghal,</hi> who are under the Teachings of <hi>James Wood,</hi> and eſpecially to ye who calls him your Paſtor, and are Members of his Church, I write un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you as I am moved of the Lord, and lay theſe following things before you to be read in the fear of God, and ſeriouſly conſider thereof, that you may no longer be deceived, but may come to ſee your own ſtate and condition truly, and to know it, and the foundation you build upon, and the rottenneſs of it; And my heart and ſoul's deſire is, That your eyes may be opened, that you may ſee the Deceiver, and how you are deceived, and may ſee the way that leads out of Deceipt into Truth, which is life to all that know it.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="response_to_James_Wood">
               <p>ON the 23 of the ſixth <hi>Month,</hi> 1657. towards the evening, hearing that <hi>Iames Wood</hi> was nigh to the place of my outward being, being come thither (as I was informed, not long after his new Ordination, and late ſending forth) to preach, as it was manifeſt by the ſending notice of it abroad among the neighbors, (amongſt whom I was neglected) though when any Miniſter of the Goſpel came to my Houſe I gave notice thereof without reſpect of perſons, (till they refuſed to come) and ſo had not the convenience of ſpeaking to him as I might have had, had not the day been ſpent; I ſent a few Lines to him and ſome Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, deſiring an Anſwer unto them; which Letter and Queries I have here inſerted, and am willing to leave it to that of God in all your Conſciences to judge from what ſpirit they proceeded.</p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>The LETTER.</head>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>James Wood,</salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>If I had had timely notice of thy being ſo near this place, I know no other, but that I should have ſeen thy face this day, but hearing not of it till this evening, I have at this time only ſent thee a few Queries, here incloſed, which I deſire thee to Anſwer before thou goeſt out of the Country; or if that time be too short for thee, take them home with thee, and ſend the Anſwers to him who thinks himſelf happy, if he be found worthy to receive a Miniſter of Christ into his houſe, called by the name of</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>James Sicklemore.</signed> 
                        <dateline>Ballinlegane, <date>
                              <hi>23. of the ſixth Month, 1657.</hi>
                           </date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <head>The Queries.</head>
                     <p n="1">1. <hi>Query,</hi> What is the everlaſting Goſpel? 2. <hi>Qu.</hi> Who is a Miniſter of the everlaſting Goſpel? &amp; how is he made a Miniſter therof? 3. <hi>Qu.</hi> Can any preach the Goſpel but he who is made a Miniſter therof? 4. <hi>Qu.</hi> Hath any Power &amp; authority to Preach the Goſpel before he is made a Miniſter thereof, &amp; is ſent, if not, then tell me? 5. <hi>Qu.</hi> What are thoſe men that have a long time profeſt themſelves to be Miniſters of the Goſpel, and have been preaching of it (as they ſay) theſe 5 or 10 years, or more, and yet after all this time, and Preaching, receives Ordination from men, and by men are choſen and ſent forth to Preach? 6. <hi>Qu.</hi> Whether thoſe who were choſen and ſent forth to Preach the Goſpel, had any certain dwelling place, or did abide 3 or 4 years, or more, in one place? 7. <hi>Qu.</hi> Who made <hi>Paul</hi> a Miniſter of the Goſpel? And who was it that ſent him to Preach? 8. <hi>Qu.</hi> What was the maintenance of Chriſts Miniſters, who by him were ſent forth, and what were they to live off? 9 <hi>Qu.</hi> Hath his Miniſters in this age any other maintenance? and when was their maintenance changed? For the ſake of the ſimple theſe are given forth, for whoſe ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction, if thou beeſt a Miniſter of the Goſpel, it will lye upon thee to Anſwer them ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Scriptures, and not to ſlight it.</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>J. S.</signed>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>And although I was willing to give him what time he would deſire for the Anſwering of thoſe <hi>Queries,</hi> and not to preſs it to him before his return, yet he refuſed to give me any other Anſwer than theſe following Lines, writ and ſent to me in the bottom of my own Letter, and ſo ſent me the <hi>Queries</hi> and my Letter again. <hi>His Letter followeth:</hi>
               </p>
               <floatingText type="letter" xml:lang="eng">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <salute>Captain <hi>Sicklemore,</hi>
                        </salute>
                     </opener>
                     <p>I have received the above written, and the incloſed, and give you only this return, That I know not your Rule for ſending abroad your <hi>Queries,</hi> nor mine to Anſwer them, they ſavouring ſo much of Contention and Contradiction, I yet think that I have ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently proved my Call to the Miniſtry before <hi>John Perrot</hi> and your Self; if not to you, yet to mine own ſatisfaction, and of many elſe who I trust fear the Lord in ſimplicity; I ſorrow to ſee
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:41149:2"/>your Zeal (if ſo it be) ſo blind: You have read ſurely <hi>Acts 13.1, 2, 3.</hi> and yet know <hi>Paul</hi> had Preach'd ſome years before: But I determine to Anſwer no more of your <hi>Queries</hi> or Demands: either by word of Mouth or Wrighting till both they and you shall breath out more of the Goſpel, This is from a ſervant of the Lord and his people in the Goſpel,</p>
                     <closer>
                        <signed>Ja. Wood.</signed>
                        <dateline>
                           <date>
                              <hi>Sixth Month, 23 day, 1657.</hi>
                           </date>
                        </dateline>
                     </closer>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>Let not <hi>James Wood</hi> think it ſtrange, or take it ill, That I direct not my ſpeech to him in Anſwer to his Letter, ſeeing he hath told me that he is determined to Anſwer no more of my Queries or Demands (though I know not, that before, I deſired any ſuch thing from him) till ſuch and ſuch a time. Yet I cannot ceaſe either from ſpeaking or writing what the Lord hath commanded. And this Anſwer is not to beget Contention as he would ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe me in part of his Letter, but to lay open the deceipt of the Deceiver, againſt whom I am a witneſs, that the ſimple may no longer be enſnared: and this for your ſakes whoſe ſimple deſires after God are not yet ſatisfied.</p>
               <p>In the beginning of his Letter he tells me, <hi>He knows not my Rule for ſending abroad my Queries, nor his to Anſwer them.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Anſw. <hi>I do not wonder if</hi> James Wood <hi>be unacquainted with my Rule for ſending my Queries to him, ſeeing he is ſo great an enemy and oppoſer of him who is my rule and guide, Chriſt Jeſus, the light of the World, who hath enlightned me, and every one that cometh into the World, and him I profeſſe and no other, and his light which shines in my conſcience which checks and condemnes for ſin do I love and own to be my rule, that ſo by it I may be ruled and guided to do the will of God as it is revealed and manifeſted in me by his eternal Word and ſpirit, by which ſpirit I was guided when I wrote thoſe Queries: And if</hi> J.W. <hi>were a Miniſter of the Goſpel of Chriſt, then could he not be ignorant of my rule, for all his Miniſters have his ſpirit which is infallible, by which all things are ſeen and tryed, and ſo that which is contrary to it comes to be known, ſo that if my ſending thoſe Queries were not from the Lord, but from another ſpirit, he would quickly have known it, if he had had the ſame ſpirit that all the Ministers of Christ had: and they that have not his ſpirit are none of his, and this ſpirit ſees and makes manifest all other ſpirits, and tryes them: Here let all the ſimple-hearted judge by what ſpirit</hi> J.W. <hi>is ruled and guided, which leaves him in ſuch an ignorant ſtate and condition, that if any one come, and ask, or ſend so him queſtions, he is forced to confeſſe he knows not their rule for ſo doing, and thinks that this is excuſe enough to get rid of them; but the ſubtilty deceives him, for hereby he shuts himſelf out from having the infallible ſpirit, which ſees, and diſcerns, and knowes all things, and makes manifeſt the hidden things of</hi> Eſau, <hi>and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veals, and shews, yea, and is the good rule, and diſcovers all other rules that is contrary to it, and judges them. But ſeeing</hi> J.W <hi>knows not his rule for Anſwering my Queries, I would deſire ſome of you to enquire of him, (for if I thould ask him, he would not tell me) What was his rule for Anſwering</hi> John Browns <hi>Queries and ſending more to him, Did he well or ill in that? if well, Why may not I ſend Queries to him, expecting an Anſwer, as well as he ſend Queries to</hi> John Brown, <hi>which were Anſwered: this is not to do as he would be done to.</hi> But <hi>I.W.</hi> makes his ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe in framing a falſe thing which he would have paſs currant for truth, &amp; that is expreſt in his next words of his Letter, <hi>(They ſavoring ſo much of Contention and Contradiction.)</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> Surely <hi>I.W.</hi> hath loſt his ſavour, if ever he was well ſeaſoned; but it is not to be expected that he which is wanting of that which doth diſcern and try truly, can never be a p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                     <desc>…</desc>
                  </gap>eſſor of that which ſavors aright; for that which cannot diſcern, cannot ſavor: And there was a generation that did call evil good, and good evil; and did put darkneſſe for light, and light for darkneſſe; and there is ſome ſuch now, and this is becauſe they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not truly diſcern: Yet admit this were true, as <hi>I.W.</hi> ſayes, it is no excuſe for his not an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwering them: would he not more have ſhewed himſelf a Servant of the Lord, and his people, in laying them open, and making manifeſt this Spirit of contention and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction, then in holding his peace? for it was the work of the Miniſters of the Goſpel to labour to beat down that Spirit where-ever they found it, and to lay open the deceit of it, that the ſimple may beware of it. But though J.W. hath ſo judged of them, it doth not make
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:41149:2"/>them ſo, they ſtand upon record to be examined and tryed by the light in every mans con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, to which I leave them to be judged, and with it I deſire you all to read them over, and ſee if this be true or falſe that J.W. accuſes them of.</p>
               <p>And although <hi>I.W.</hi> wil not anſwer my queries, he finding them tending to the enquiring out of the call of the Miniſters of the Goſpel, to the preaching of it, and he profeſſing to be in that work himſelf, knows that his muſtneeds come to an examination and tryal, whether it be according to the Scriptures, even by the anſwering of theſe Queries, if according to the Scriptures; therefore he muſt needs ſay ſomething, (which is indeedas good as nothing) in vindication of his own Call, as you may perceive in the next words of his Letter, though neither in my Letter or queries did I inquire of J.W. any thing concerning his own call to the Miniſtry in particular, ſo that he might have ſpared theſe lines: Yet he need not boaſts for can he have ſufficiently proved his Call to the Miniſtry of God, when as yet he is not in that Miniſtry? The Miniſters of God had the Seals of their Miniſtry, and they reaped the fruits of their labours: And <hi>Timothy</hi> was <hi>Pauls</hi> Son, and ſo was <hi>Oniſimus,</hi> and he had babes which were begotten by him, and little children of whom he travelled till Chriſt was formed in them. Now I would ask of you who have been a long time, and are yet under his Miniſtry, How many of you, yea, is there anie one of you can witneſſe a begetting into God by him? and can any of you by his labour, ſay Chriſt is formed in you? can you witneſſe ſuch a ſtate? This is a high ſtate, friends, and is not a talk and a profeſſion, but a poſſeſsion, and muſt be witneſſed in deed and truth. Again, The Miniſtry of God was for the perfecting of the Saints; and if J.W. hath not by his Miniſtry brought any thus far, he never yet ſaw the end of his Miniſtrie, neither ſhall he ever be able to bring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of you into that ſtate, who cannot witneſſe ſuch a ſtate himſelf, neither can believe that ſuch a ſtate can be attained to in this life, then may not he as good hold his peace as preach?</p>
               <p>But friends, be not deceived, the Miniſtrie of God was and is ſent to turn people from darkneſſe to light; and he that is a Miniſter of God, is a Miniſter of light, and muſt mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter from the light, that ſo ſouls may be brought out of darkneſſe, wherein lies imperfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, unto the light which is perfect, that they may be children of light, bringing forth the fruits of the light, which none can that hate the light, and will not bring their deeds to the light, that they may be made manifeſt: And friends, when I ſpeak of the light, I ſpeak of the true light which lighteth every man that cometh into the world, which <hi>John</hi> bare witneſſe of, Chriſt Jeſus, which <hi>Paul</hi> preached, and was a Miniſter of, which whoſoever follows, comes to have the light of life, and he that hates it goes into condemnation: And this is in every ones conſcience, checking and reproving him for, and convincing him of evil; and if they would follow it, it will lead from fin and iniquitie, which it condemns in all, into righteouſneſſe and holineſſe; and though this be in every one, yet every one doth not love it, and follow it; for they who are in ſin, and living in it, and in the world, and are not redeemed from it, but are in the luſts and pleaſures of it, and cuſtoms and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhions of it, which are vain, are ſuch who act contrary to the light in them, which checks them for it: And all who are in pride and covetouſneſſe, and in many words, which are vain and unneceſſarie, theſe are all from the light turned, which condemns in the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence for it, whom God will not juſtifie; and none but thoſe who love the light, and follow it, comes to know redemption and ſalvation by Chriſt Jeſus, who is the light, who ſaves his people from their ſins, and as many as believe in the light of the world, receives power to become the Sons of God, and none elſe.</p>
               <p>But this light J. W. is ſo far from being a Miniſter of, that he cannot own it to bee of God, or from Chriſt, but hath called it natural, even that light which is in every mans conſcience; and ſo he hath made himſelf manifeſt to be an oppoſer of that which checks and condemns ſin in every mans conſcience, and to be out of the miniſtry of God, who is light; and therefore though he thinks he hath ſufficientlie proved his Call to this mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:41149:3"/>of God, I am ſure he is miſtaken, and his thoughts deceive him; for that in his conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence which is of God, ſhal teſtifie to his face, that he is a reſiſter of it, &amp; walks contrary to it, &amp; to all who are come into the true fear of the Lord, he is known; &amp; I doubt not but to ſom of you in whom I know there are ſimple deſires after God, he is partly known and ſeen, and many of his practiſes I know you cannot own; let that of God in your conſciences ſpeak. Yet nevertheleſſe J.W. hath little reaſon to deſire that dayes work to be brought to remembrance; for though he ſpent much time to tell a ſtory of his inclinations to, and qualifications for the work of the miniſtry from his youth, up, (after ſuch a manner as he never found any of the miniſters of Chriſt boaſting, for they alwaies denied their for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer life) which he called his inward call; yet he told us alſo of an outward call, which was by man, as being approved of by man; and for all his inward qualifications, yet he attributed ſomething to his humane art and learning, of which though he ſpoke ſlightly, ſeemingly, yet he added it to all the reſt as a help in the work; and after all this large Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion which he made, declaring how he was called to the miniſtry, I leave it to you all who were there preſent, to judge whether or no he did prove that his call to be according to the Scriptures, &amp; which of the miniſters of Chriſt did he inſtance or bring for an example that was ſo called, though he profeſſed that that ſhould be the Rule to try both his and <hi>John Perrots</hi> miniſtry by.</p>
               <p>The Diſcourſe as I very well remember, was much upon <hi>Pauls</hi> Call, who indeed was an able miniſter of Chriſt; and we find, that although he was a man who was brought up at the feet of <hi>Gamaliel,</hi> yet in all his ſpeaking of his call to that work, he never made menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of it any otherwiſe then declaring it to be his former life, wherein he <hi>was zealous in per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecuting the way of God;</hi> and in his preaching alſo, all that wiſdom was laid aſide; for when he came to the <hi>Corinthians, he came not with excellency of ſpeech, nor of wiſdom, nor with the enticing words of mans wiſdom, which is the worlds wiſdom;</hi> and if he would have boaſted thereof, he had much to ſpeak of, read <hi>Phil.</hi> chap. 3. v. 4, 5, 6, 7, 8. <hi>yet all that which was gain to him formerly, he counted it loſſe for Chriſt, and for the excellency of the knowledge of Chriſt Jeſus, wherein his Miniſtry ſtood; neither would he at any time own his call or ſending to be of men, or by man, but by Jeſus Chriſt, and by the will of God,</hi> as you may read, <hi>Gal.</hi> 1.1. and in the beginning of moſt of his Epiſtles, though J.W. that day did endeavor to prove it to be by man, by <hi>Acts</hi> 13.1, 2, 3. which is the place alſo he quotes in his Letter to me; who ever can read that place with underſtanding, will ſee it doth not contradict <hi>Pauls</hi> ſaying <hi>He was an Apoſtle, not by man,</hi> though it be alwayes the Prieſts work to make the Scriptures claſh one againſt another, that ſo they may get money of the people to reconcile them (as they ſay) by their moanings and interpretations: But this is deceit, and the Scriptures are true, and agree in one, being all given forth by one ſpirit, which doth not contradict it ſelf; and by no other ſpirit can they be read nor underſtood, but to all other ſpirits are a para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſealed. It is there ſaid, <hi>That ſuch and ſuch who were in the Church, as they miniſtered to the Lord, and fasted, the Holy Ghoſt ſaid, Separate me</hi> Barnabas <hi>and</hi> Saul <hi>for the work whereunto</hi> I <hi>have called them;</hi> here the Holy Ghoſt had called them, and the Holy Ghoſt commanded the ſeparation, and the Holy Ghoſt ſent them away, as you may read in the fourth verſe, that they departed, being ſent by the Holy Ghoſt; and this is one with what is written in the third verſe, but the unlearned wreſt it, for the Holy Ghoſt gave order for their ſepara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and alſo ſent them away.</p>
               <p>And I'le appeal to you all who were that day preſent, did <hi>I. W.</hi> prove his call <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o be thus? did he name any that were in the Church, that were Prophets and Teachers, that miniſtered to the Lord and faſted, and as they did ſo, that the Holy Ghoſt ſaid, <hi>ſeparate me</hi> James Wood <hi>for the work whereunto I have called him;</hi> he did not witneſs any ſuch thing to us then: yea, and I queſtion much whether his late ordination and ſending was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to that of <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas;</hi> ſome of you perhaps might be preſent, you can tell whether that day was ſpent in faſting and praying, or feaſting and praying; and if you
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:41149:3"/>can read with the ſpirit, I defire you to compare <hi>Pauls</hi> ſeparation, in <hi>Act.</hi> 13. with J.<hi>W.</hi> his late ſeparation: I would ask whether thoſe men who laid their hands on J.<hi>W.</hi> recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved an immediate command from the Holy Ghoſt ſo to do, as thoſe did, who miniſtered to the Lord and faſted: And though J.<hi>W.</hi> tells me, that ſure I know <hi>Paul</hi> had preached ſome years before that, and ſo would fain cover his late ſending forth with this practice, and excuſe its not being done ſooner, yet the deceit is ſeen, for the covering is too ſhort; for though <hi>Paul</hi> had been preaching before, yet he was returned from <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> with <hi>Barnabas,</hi> having fulfilled their Miniſtry, <hi>Acts</hi> 12.25. and that being done, the Holy Ghoſt ſends them another way to preach; for we ſhall alwayes find, that when the work was don in one place they departed to another, and ſtaid not in one place many years in a ſetled outward habitation, &amp; they went ſtill as they were ſent by the Holy Ghoſt, who never ſuffered them to be idle, no not a day was allowed them for their recreation, or the exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe of their bodies, for their health; for this was their daily exerciſe, to be doing the will of him that ſent him, and <hi>Pauls</hi> body bore the marks of our Lord Jeſus. Now ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther J.<hi>W.</hi> muſt make it appear, that he hath fulfilled his former Miniſtry, as <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> had, or elſe he cannot plead a right to this ſending of <hi>Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> in <hi>Act.</hi> 13. whether he hath done that, let that of God in his conſcience judge; and whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he hath manifeſted ſuch a thing to any of you, let that of God in your conſciences ſpeak and declare; Nay, its much to be feared, that inſtead of fulfilling his Miniſtry, he is fallen back from much of it; witneſs his ſprinkling of infants, which once he could not do, even ſince he firſt pretended a call to the Miniſtry, and his ſinging of <hi>Davids</hi> Pſalms, which once he ſeemingly endeavoured to take off people from, and his now declaring it his judgement, that by the right of <hi>Magna Charta,</hi> Miniſters may receive tythes, which once he did believe, was not according to the practice of the Miniſters of the Goſpel; he might be traced in much more, of which, ſome of you cannot be ignorant, as his once pleading againſt perſecution of any for conſcience ſake, of which he himſelf would not be counted guilty; yet if you will examine ſtrickly, what made him ſo earneſt againſt <hi>Edward Erbery,</hi> who was a priſoner for the witneſs of a good conſcience, when he was called before the Rulers? did he there plead againſt that perſecution? or was he not very zealous in agrivating the crime? (ſo accuſed to be) which did not ſo much concern him in particular, as it did <hi>Edward Eyres.</hi> And again, that day wherein J.<hi>W.</hi> thinks he hath ſufficiently proved his call to the Miniſtry, you may remember that after he had taken up much time in declaring his inward and outward qualifications, and inward and outward call, which is not according to the Scriptures; there was ſome queſtions asked concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning his practice, which was compared with the practices of the Miniſters of Chriſt in the Scriptures; whether he proved his preſent practice ſo to be, I'le leave to all the honeſt hearted there to judge; as concerning his maintenance, which he could not deny, but was above 100 <abbr>l.</abbr> and ſalary, which he confeſſed he went once a quarter to demand and receive at <hi>Cork,</hi> though he was confident to affirm, that he took not thought what he ſhould eat or drink; did he not then contradict himſelf? and could he find ſuch an example among all the Miniſters of Chriſt? Friends, there is none; for all his Miniſters obeyed his commands for their maintenance; <hi>freely ye have received, freely give; and into whatſoever houſe ye enter, and they receive you, there abide till you depart;</hi> but it is in no place ſaid, <hi>go to ask for meat;</hi> for they were not to take thought concerning it, but to truſt their Maſter Chriſt, which thing when it was asked of J.<hi>W.</hi> if he could not do it, he moſt impudently breaks out, and asked <hi>John Perrot, If he would have him to hold up his mouth, and look for God to drop bread from heaven into it;</hi> one of the vaineſt expreſſions that ever I heard come out of a mans mouth, profeſsing a ſeparation from the world, as he doth; and being charged with his feaſting, which he was particularly exerciſed in that day, he affirmed, <hi>that half of the Creation needed not have been, if men might not eat more then would ſatisfie nature;</hi> would not this man be wiſer then God? or would he not make God the Author of gluttony and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:41149:4"/>exceſs, and make this a cloak for it; or doth he not meaſure the wiſdom of God by his own luſt? which becauſe he hath allowed him out of the common treaſury, neer 200 <abbr>l.</abbr> 
                  <hi>per annum,</hi> cannot be ſatisfied without the ſpending of it all, of which he might be aſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to boaſt; is he not an evil example to you in this beaſtly practice? and yet he would cloak it with the Saints love-feaſts, which were never made for the rich; I know you that are ſimple and honeſt in any meaſure, cannot own his practice in that thing, nor his vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in his pictures, which is all odious in the ſight of God, and ſtinks in his noſtrils; and what think you of his bowling and kettle-pin playing, which he that day pleaced for; was that according to the Scriptures? Friends, ſeriouſly conſider of all theſe things, and then ſee whether J.<hi>W.</hi> his firſt ſending, or his laſt were according to that of <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                        <desc>…</desc>
                     </gap>s,</hi> and judge what cauſe this man had to boaſt of that dayes work, wherein he thinks he did ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently prove his call to the Miniſtry.</p>
               <p>More of his Letter; <hi>I ſorrow to ſee your zeal (if ſo it be) ſo blind:</hi> This expreſsion is plainly in hypocriſie, for his joy and ſorrow ſtands in one nature; he calls it <hi>my zeal,</hi> in writing the Letter and Queries, and he ſayes it is <hi>blind,</hi> and yet he queſtions whether it be my <hi>zeal</hi> or no; is not this confuſion? but why ſhould this be cauſe of ſorrow to him or any Miniſter of the Goſpel to meet with ſuch a Letter and Queries; verily I am not aſhamed that any honeſt heart ſhould ſee them, yet this man is ſorry: when my <hi>zeal</hi> was hot and furious in acting ſin, and running into vanity, then he was not at all ſorry, or he never expreſſed it to me, but rather was joyful, as I could perceive, becauſe he was one with me therein, witneſs the time we ſpent together in bowling and kettle-pin playing, and in needleſs diſcourſe, wherein our fellowſhip then ſtood; and my zeal was great, yet he never then told me it was <hi>blind,</hi> or that he <hi>ſorrowed</hi> for it: But now I being by the power of God redeemed from thoſe vain practices, and brought to ſtand as a witneſs againſt them, and am now entring into another ſtate and condition, and ſeeking a better King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom and its righteouſneſs; now he is ſorry and herein he is not unlike all the reſt of his brethren, that are of that profeſsion; for take a man that will run with them all the week long to feaſting, and ſporting, and playing, which he calls <hi>recreation of the body for its health;</hi> and let him be never ſo zealous herein, and be never ſo much exerciſed in vain and idle diſcourſe, ſo it be witty and pleaſant, as all ſin is, and yet go to hear them preach one or two dayes in the week, and confeſs all is true that they ſay, and own them to be ſent of God, and ſo honour them, and cry them up for good men; theſe men may live ſecurely without any reproof from them inparticular, ſo long as their mouths be fild, they crypeace, <hi>and ſuch a one shall be daubed with untempered morter,</hi> &amp; his ſtate is counted good enough, tho he die to morrow, he ſhal be ſav'd by Chriſt; &amp; ſo the poor ſoul is deceived, &amp; dies in his ſins. But if this perſon comes ever to be ſenſible of its ſad ſtate that it is in by reaſon of ſin which daily oppreſſes the ſoul, and carries it captive; and by the light of Chriſt comes to have his eyes opened, whereby he ſees that he hath been deceived, by ſuch who have cryed peace to him, when he was daily overcome with ſin; and now comes to ſee that there is no peace to the wicked, and ſo begins to make enquiry after a way to get out of that State, and to be redeemed from it, and to take heed to the Light, which all along checked him in his former vanity, and to love it, and follow it, which leads from ſin unto righteouſneſs, and works a change, and brings him to be a witneſs againſt his ſins, and againſt all his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer life which he lived in under the teachings of ſuch blind guides, this man is called by them an Apoſtate, they are ſorry to ſee this mans zeal now for God, and they call i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> blind, and ſay he is deceived and deluded.</p>
               <p>Then in the latter end of his Letter he calls himſelf, <hi>A ſervant of the Lords, and his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the Goſpel:</hi> How far God hath owned his ſervice, let the fruits of his miniſtery theſe many years laſt paſt in this Town of <hi>Youghall</hi> teſtifie, and in this long ſervice let him pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce and manifeſt what fruits hath been brought forth to God, and how many hath been brought into the Vineyard of God, where no unfruitful tree muſt be, without being out
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:41149:4"/>down; &amp; whatſervice he hath done for his people; and who J.<hi>W.</hi> calls <hi>the Lords people</hi> would be enquired after; ſure, there's not many in the town of <hi>Youghall,</hi> among whom he hath bin ſo long preaching, wil own him to be their Servant, ſeeing he refuſes to do what ſervice they deſire from him; yet no doubt but they help pay him his wages, &amp; if we ſhould make a ſtrict enquiry among his own people and Church, we ſhall find that though he calls him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf their ſervant, yet moſt of them call him Maſter, ſo that upon a true ſearch, this wil prove but words, and little leſs then a bare complement.</p>
               <p>Friends and people, <hi>At the times of ignorance God wincked, but now he commandeth all men every where to repent; Be not deceived, God will not be mocked. Not every one that cries Lord Lord, ſhall enter into the kingdom of heaven; but he that doth the will of my Father,</hi> ſaith Chriſt: <hi>In the fear God, examine your ſelves, whoſe will you are doing daily; if you will do the will of God, you muſt deny your own wills in all things, and they that are doing evil and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitting ſin, are not doing the will of God:</hi> 'tis not a talk of Repentance, and forſaking ſin will ſtand you in ſtead, or give you true peace, but a forſaking of it indeed and in truth, and <hi>a putting off the old man with his deeds,</hi> and <hi>a orucifying of the fleſh with the affections and Luſts muſt be witneſſed, before you can ſay you are Chriſts, and witneſs him in you, righteouſneſs, and ſanctification and redemption;</hi> tis not a giving up your names to be written in J. <hi>W.</hi> his book, or any other paper that will adminiſter true comfort to you, but you muſt come to know your names written in the Lambs book of life, where nothing that deſiles can come; pure Religion ſtands not in a ſeparation that is ſenſual, and in a ſhew only, but in being unſpotted with the world; I judge none of you; Search your ſelves with the Light that comes from Jeſus, which is nigh you, and it will truly ſhow you your own ſtates and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions, and when you ſee your ſelves, beleeve none that will daub you, and tell you a ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry contrary to what you ſee with your eye, which is the Light of the body: Friends, This Light will ſhew you all that ever you did, and makes manifeſt all things that have been, and are done in ſecret, and judges all that is evil, and juſtifies none, but ſuch who to it are obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient: this is Gods faithful witneſs in your Conſciences, which doth either accuſe or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe; if it accuſe, beleeve not any that would excuſe; if it excuſe, none can condemn; if any one ſin, it accuſes, and brings trouble upon the evil doer, unto whom there is no peace; Therefore do not live ſecurely; but try your ſelves, and what the light of Chriſt in you ſhews you to be evil, abſtain from it even in its appearance: Love the light, and bring all your deeds to it, that they may be made manifeſt where they are wrought; follow the light of the world wherewith you are enlightened, that you may come to have the light of life which gives victory over death, and brings out of its ſnare, and from under its dominion; ſin is deaths kingdom, and all who are in ſin, and by it carryed captive are in its ſnare, and out of the kingdom of God, into which nothing that defiles can enter: Friends, look out no longer for a teacher, for the teachers that are without cauſe you to erre; but the word is nigh you, in your hearts and mouths, turn in to hear it ſpeak, and it will ſhew you the way you ſhould walk in; there is a meaſure of the gift of God commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to you all in particular, and the grace of God hath largely appeared to ſome of you; it teaches all that loves it <hi>to deny all ungodlineſs and worldly lusts, and to live righteouſly, ana ſoberly in this preſent evil world, this will bring you to the Repentance not to be repented of,</hi> this is that which waſheth and ſprinkleth and purgeth the conſcience from dead works to ſerve the living God? Every ſin is a dead work, he that ſerves ſin is free from Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, he that doth ſin is of the devil: Friends, Beware I write nothing, but what that of God in your conſciences bears witneſs to, thats the light; if you love your own ſouls, love the light that is in you, that checks you for ſin, and follow it; it leads from ſin unto Chriſt the Saviour who ſaves from ſin, <hi>Who is in you, except ye be Reprobates:</hi> it leads out of the world al that follow it, into the kingdom of heaven, which is within you, if you beleeve in <hi>the light who lighteth every one that cometh into the World,</hi> you will com to the faith which purifies, and to the hope which purifies, <hi>Chriſt in you the hope of glory;</hi> this hope will not fail you, when al
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:41149:5"/>other hopes ſhall periſh. So priſe your time, and neglect not this day of Gods viſiting you, but come to the light, and try all your thoughts, words, and wayes by it; and all ſpirits this will diſcover, all ſeducers and deceivers, and the falſe prophets ſhew you; and it will bring you, if you it follow, to the true prophet, which whoſoever will not hear, ſhall be cut off.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And all you who are burthened with ſin, and feels the weight of it, and are weary, and would be eaſed, and are hungring and thirſting after ſatisfaction and reſt, and true peace, of which you were never yet made partakers, neither could you meet with, or obtain in all your profeſſion; I ſay unto you from the Lord, ceaſe from looking out for help, and running from one hill to another to find out the way of the Lord, for your help is nigh unto you, and he is not afar off; and till you come to turn in your minds, and to take heed unto that which works the deſire in you, you ſhall never come to be ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied; for the deſire is not in your ſelves, or in any thing you can do, but is wrought by God, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but ſomething from God muſt ſatisfie; and what may be known of him is manifeſt in you, and the deſire is within, and the content alſo is to be found there; for this is the cauſe that you y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 chunk">
                        <desc>…</desc>
                     </gap> ly down in ſorrow, becauſe you ſeek to that which is without for help, and art going to Egypt for aid, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get him who is near at hand, and ſo the true deſires many times are loſt, and you reſt ſatisfied for a ſeaſon, till the witneſſe in you ariſes again, and ſhews you your ſtate, then you are more unſatisfied than before; and your Teachers to whom you ſeek, endeavours to heal this wound alſo, and will bid you believe in Chriſt, and lay hold upon him [good words] but yet you are ignorant of him to be in you, and of his life and power you are not partakers, who waſhes, and ſanctifies, and purifies, and makes clean. Therefore friends mind the light which is of God, which ſhews your ſinful ſtate and ſad condition; and follow is, that by it you may be led out of that ſtate, and come to witneſſe a new ſtate and a new birth, which is of God, which ſins not, and to find, and enjoy, and poſſeſſe the true peace, which paſſeth underſtanding, which they who are in the world knows not, nor doth not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> all you who are running into ſin with delight, and are drinking iniquity like water, and have forgotten God, who is not in all your thoughts, and have ſet your faces againſt inſtruction &amp; reproof, and shuts your eyes, and ſtops your ears, leaſt you ſhould ſee with your eyes, and hear with your ears, and be converted, but are living in your ſins, and in them are ſecure, and cannot endure to hear of a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> of holyneſſe, and righteouſneſſe, and purity, but are oppoſers of it, and perſecuters of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> who witneſſe it: I ſay from the Lord, Gods hand is over you, and his arm is ſtretched out againſt you, and an utter deſolation he will make of you except you repent ſpeedily, and turn from the evil of your ways, and ſeek the Lord by unfeigned repentance; for the time of his ſtriving with you is well nigh paſt, and the day is coming upon you that ſorrow ſhall take hold uyon you, and trouble ſhall come upon you as an armed man, and you ſhall ſeek for help, and ſhall not find it, becauſe you have been <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>, and rebellious, and ſtiff-necked againſt the Lord, and would not hearken when by his light which is in you he called, but from day to day reſiſted his ſpirit, and quenched it in you when it did ariſe in your conſciences to condemn you for ſin, and have ſlain his witneſſe in you, and are making merry over it; behold, it ſhall ariſe as an evidence againſt you in the day of Gods pleading with you, and you ſhall not be able to ſtand: Therefore take warning in time before the evil day comes upon you, leſt your dayes be ſhortned, and you dye in your ſins, and you become a curſed example to all the workers of iniquity.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>All people, let the love and long-ſufferings of the Lord God move you and lead you to repentance.</hi>
               </p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>James Sicklemore.</signed>
               </closer>
            </div>
            <trailer>The End.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
